Guide to the Lois Williams Bry Collection of Eugene O'Neill, Jr.
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lois Williams Bry collection of Eugene O'Neill, Jr.
1925-1986
1936-1950
YCAL MSS 125
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.4
(5 boxes)
Letters from Eugene O'Neill, Jr. to Lois Williams Bry, 1925-49; printed versions of O'Neill, Jr.'s articles and reviews, many inscribed to Bry; and subject files (mainly clippings) collected by Bry about O'Neill, Jr., his friends, and his family.
Bry, Lois Williams
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lois Williams Bry, 1986.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 5: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
LOIS WILLIAMS BRY
Eugene O'Neill, Jr. and Lois Williams Bry were childhood friends in Douglaston (New York, N.Y.) and remained close friends throughout O'Neill, Jr.'s life. They corresponded regularly until 1949, the year before O'Neill, Jr.'s death. At the time of his death, Bry had lived for many years with her husband and children on a ranch in Ennis, Montana, where O'Neill, Jr. visited them several times. A biographical sketch of O'Neill, Jr. is provided in the Eugene O'Neill, Jr. Collection (YCAL MSS 126).
Scope and Contents
The Lois Williams Bry Collection of Eugene O'Neill, Jr. contains materials concerning Eugene O'Neill, Jr. that Bry received from Eugene O'Neill, Jr. or that she collected. These include correspondence, writings of Eugene O'Neill, Jr., clippings, and programs, spanning the years 1925 to 1986. The bulk of the material, however, dates from 1936 to 1950. The collection is organized into three series: Correspondence, Writings, and Subject Files, and is housed in five boxes.
Series I, Correspondence, is organized into two subseries: Eugene O'Neill, Jr. Letters and Third Party Correspondence. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically. The Eugene O'Neill, Jr. Letters mainly contains letters from O'Neill, Jr. to Bry, spanning the years 1925 to 1949. (There is an unexplained gap from 1929 to 1934.) This collection does not contain Bry's letters to O'Neill, Jr., which were returned to her by Elsie and Frank S. Meyer after O'Neill, Jr.'s death in 1950.
O'Neill, Jr. wrote detailed letters to Bry, discussing his work, his marriages, and his personal life; many of his letters mention O'Neill, Jr.'s Newfoundland dog, Cabot, whom he brought to live with the Brys on their ranch. There are also two letters to Bry's husband, N. William Bry, and one letter to Bry's sister.
Third Party Correspondence consists of letters from friends to Bry about O'Neill, Jr. and his death. There is also one letter to Bry from O'Neill, Jr.'s first wife, Mary Elizabeth Green, dated 10 March 1936, regarding a possible summer visit to Montana.
Series II, Writings, consists chiefly of printed versions of O'Neill, Jr.'s writings, many inscribed by him to Bry. The series is organized into four subseries: Articles, Reviews, Other Writings, and Writings of Others. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically. The first subseries, Articles, contains printed versions of O'Neill, Jr.'s articles in the field of classical studies. The second subseries, Reviews, contains printed versions and clippings of printed versions of O'Neill, Jr.'s reviews of other authors' works in the field of classical studies. The third subseries, Other Writings, contains a letter by O'Neill, Jr. to the editor of The Key Reporter, and the printed version of O'Neill, Jr.'s 1947 commencement address at Connecticut College. The fourth subseries, Writings of Others, contains a printed version of an article by Julian L. Rogatz, on a medical topic, inscribed to Bry and her husband. There is also a holograph version of a poem by an unidentified author.
Series III, Subject Files, is arranged alphabetically and mostly contains material collected after O'Neill, Jr.'s death. This includes clippings about friends, family, and associates of O'Neill, Jr., including Agnes Boulton, Oona Chaplin, and Paul Robeson. There are programs for three of Eugene O'Neill's plays, as well as numerous clippings about him and his work. There is also a program from O'Neill, Jr.'s commencement from Yale in 1932 and a 1936-37 course catalog for Yale that includes information about courses that O'Neill, Jr. taught.
Greek language -- Study and teaching; Greek literature -- Study and teaching; Latin language -- Study and teaching; Latin literature -- Study and teaching; Bry, Lois Williams; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953; Yale University -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1925-1951; Series I; 0.6; (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized into two subseries: Eugene O'Neill, Jr. Letters and Third Party Correspondence. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
  - EUGENE O'NEILL, JR. LETTERS
    - To Lois Williams Bry
      - Correspondence, 1925 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, 1926 Jan-May (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence, 1926 Jul-Oct (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Poem enclosed in letter dated 1926 Jul 7.
      - Correspondence, 1927-36 Feb (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence, 1936 Sep-Oct (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence, 1936 Nov-37 Apr (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence, 1937 Jun-Jul (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence, 1937 Sep-Nov (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence, 1937 Dec-38 Feb (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence, 1938 Mar-Sep (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence, 1938 Oct-39 Feb (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence, 1939 Apr-Aug (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Correspondence, 1939 Sep-40 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Correspondence, 1941 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Correspondence, 1941 Sep-42 Jun (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Correspondence, 1942 Oct-43 May (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Correspondence, 1943 Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 17)
        Two photographs (portrait of EO in pin-striped suit, 2 versions) enclosed in letter dated 1943 Nov 22.
      - Correspondence, 1944 Apr-Dec (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Correspondence, 1945 Feb-46 Jun (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Correspondence, 1946 Dec-48 Jan (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Correspondence, 1948 Feb-May (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Correspondence, 1948 Dec-49 Feb (Box 2, Folder 22)
        Photograph of rented house in Woodstock (N.Y.) enclosed in letters dated 1948 Dec 22 and 1949 Feb 1.
      - Correspondence, 1949, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 23)
        Poems enclosed in letters dated 1949 Jul 23 and 1949 Dec 24.
      - Three empty mailing envelopes, 1945, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - To N. William Bry, 1939, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - To Dork, [1938 Dec] (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    To Lois Williams Bry
    - Greene, Mary Elizabeth, 1936 Mar 10 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Jourdon, Judythe, 1950-51 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Lenart, Gertrude, [1950 Sep] (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Meyer, Elsie Meyer, Frank S., 1950-51 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - ----, Mit, 1950, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Writings, 1934-1947; Series II; 0.2; (1 box)
  Series II, Writings, is organized into four subseries: Articles, Reviews, Other Writings, and Writings of Others. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically.
  - ARTICLES
    - "The Importance of Final Syllables in Greek Verse," article, printed version, Transactions of the American Philological Association, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      Inscribed to LWB.
    - "The Localization of Metrical Word-Types in the Greek Hexameter: Homer, Hesiod, and the Alexandrians," printed version, Yale Classical Studies, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - "Note on Phrynichus' Phoenissae and Aeschylus' Persae, printed version, Classical Philology, 1942 Oct (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - "The Prologue of the Troades of Euripides," printed version, Transactions of the American Philological Association, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - "Word-Accents and Final Syllables in Latin Verse," printed version, Transactions of the American Philological Association, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - REVIEWS
    - "The Attic Pattern," clipping of printed version, The New York Times Book Review, 1945 Jan 28 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      Review of Paideia: The Ideals of Greek Culture by Werner Jaeger. Inscribed to LWB.
    - Beede, Grace Lucile. Vergil and Aratus, a Study in the Art of Translation. Review of, printed version, American Journal of Philology, [1936] (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - "Down Pindar's 'Impetuous, Dithyrambic Tide,'" clipping of printed version, The New York Times Book Review, 1947 Apr 6 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      Review of The Odes of Pindar translated by Richmond Lattimore.
    - "England's Golden Age," clipping of printed version, The New York Times Book Review, 1947 Apr 20 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      Review of The Portable Elizabethan Reader edited by Hiram Haydn.
    - "Famous Voyage, Cut-Rate," clipping of printed version, The New York Times Book Review, 1946 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      Review of Homer's Odyssey translated by E. V. Rieu. Inscribed to LWB.
    - "Finest Intellect of Antiquity," clipping of printed version, The Saturday Review of Literature, 1946 Dec 21 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      Review of The Politics of Aristotle translated by Ernest Barker.
    - Fitts, Dudley and Robert Fitzgerald, trans. The Antigone of Sophocles. Review of, printed version, American Journal of Philology, 1939 Oct (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - "Homeric Hexameters," clipping of printed version, The New York Times Book Review, 1944 Nov 5 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      Review of Homer's Iliad translated by William Benjamin Smith and Walter Miller. Inscribed to LWB.
    - Murray, Gilbert. Aeschylus, the Creator of Tragedy. Review of, printed version, Classical Weekly, 1941 Jan 6 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - "Murray on the Greeks," clipping of printed version, The New York Times Book Review, 1947 May 18 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      Review of Greek Studies by Gilbert Murray.
    - Nonnos. Dionysiaca. Review of, printed version, American Journal of Philology (2 copies), 1944 Jul (Box 3, Folder 47)
      One copy inscribed to LWB.
    - Page, Denys Lionel. Euripides. Medea. Review of, printed version, American Journal of Philology, 1939 Oct (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Schadewaldt, Wolfgang. Die Niobe des Aischylos. Review of, printed version, Classical Philology, 1935 Jan (Box 3, Folder 49)
      Inscribed to LWB and NWB. Includes note.
    - Schütze, Kurt. Beiträge zum Verständnis der Phainomena Arats. Review of, printed version, Gnomon, 1938 Mar (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Trevelyan, H. C., trans. Euripides. Medea. Review of, printed version, Classical Weekly, 1940 Nov 18 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - "Values From Above," clipping of printed version, The New York Times Book Review, 1945 Feb 25 (Box 3, Folder 52)
      Review of Plato and Modern Education by Richard Livingstone. Inscribed to LWB.
    - Wifstrand, Albert. Von Kallimachos zu Nonnos, metrischstilistiche Untersuchungen zur späteren griechischen Epik und zu verwandten Gedichtgattungen. Review of, printed version, American Journal of Philology, 1936 Jul (Box 3, Folder 53)
      Inscribed to LWB and NWB.
  - OTHER WRITINGS
    - "Is This the End of the Battle?," letter to editor, printed version, The Key Reporter, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 54)
      With note by EO, Jr. on card.
    - "On Certain Offices - Commencement Address," printed version, Connecticut College Alumnae News, 1947 Aug (Box 3, Folder 55)
      With note by EO, Jr.
  - WRITINGS OF OTHERS
    - Rogatz, Julian L. "The Schilling Blood Count As an Aid in the Diagnosis of Acute Appendicitis in Children," article, printed version, The Journal of Pediatrics, 1934 Jun (Box 3, Folder 56)
      Inscribed by Rogatz to NWB and LWB.
    - Unidentified. "Let others wander far, let others taste...," poem, holograph, 1936 May 11 (Box 3, Folder 57)
- Subject Files, 1932-1986; Series III; 0.4; (1 box)
  Series III, Subject Files, is arranged alphabetically. Folders contain clippings unless otherwise specified.
  - Boulton, Agnes, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Bowen, Croswell (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Chaplin, Oona Chaplin, Charlie, 1942-77 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - O'Neill, Carlotta Monterey, 1970 Nov 21 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - O'Neill, Eugene
    - Programs for Long Day's Journey Into Night, Strange Interlude, and More Stately Mansions, 1956, 1963, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 62-63)
    - Postcard of photograph by Erwin Blumenfeld, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Clipping of reproduction of painting by Stuart Davis, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Biographical clippings, 1936-85, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 65-67)
    - Clippings regarding writings, 1946-86, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 68-70)
  - O'Neill, Eugene, Jr., 1947-72, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - O'Neill, Shane Rudraighe, 1960-77 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Robeson, Paul, 1972-78, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Yale University
    - Commencement program, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Course catalog, 1936-37 (Box 4, Folder 75)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.2; (1 box)
  Box 5, Restricted Fragile, contains fragile originals. The material is arranged in folder order and may only be seen with the permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies or photographic prints have been substituted in the main files for reference use.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folders 4, 8-10, 12, 19 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Box 2, folder 28 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Box 2, folder 29 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Box 2, folder 30 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Box 3, folder 37 (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Box 3, folder 39 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Box 3, folder 40 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Box 3, folder 41 (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Box 3, folder 42 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Box 3, folder 44 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Box 3, folder 46 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Box 3, folder 52 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Box 4, folder 58 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Box 4, folder 59 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Box 4, folder 60 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Box 4, folder 61 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Box 4, folder 71 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Box 4, folder 72 (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Box 4, folder 73 (Box 5, Folder 94)